The ME-163B
Komet.
The Schwerer Gustav gun.
The V-1 pulsejet flying bomb.
The Horten 229 flying wing.
You might think you know what enabled
Adolf Hitler to march [music] his way
across Europe.
But it's these secret weapons which
nearly cost the Allies [music] the
Second World War.
Hitler's engineers and scientists
developed [music] some of the most
revolutionary and terrifying instruments
of death.
>> In terms of military technology,
Germany was streets ahead of the Allies.
>> Now on World's Weirdest Weapons, we go
underground to uncover the classified
Nazi weapons
that could have turned the tide of the
war in Germany's favor.
By the summer of 1940, Adolf Hitler's
German armies are triumphantly marching
across Western Europe.
>> Almost everything the Germans do seems
to turn to a massive success.
They do have very good armed forces
indeed.
They are attacking unprepared countries,
very often neutral countries.
>> They have defeated Poland,
Denmark,
Norway,
the Netherlands,
and Belgium.
And they've driven the British out of
France [music] at Dunkirk.
By early 1941,
German General Erwin Rommel is storming
his way through North Africa.
But Hitler isn't just obsessed with
conquering [music] countries.
He's obsessed with weaponry, pushing his
scientists and engineers to produce some
of the most terrifying weapons [music]
imaginable to give him the edge.
When he turns east, he needs that edge
more than ever.
The Russian army is a formidable enemy.
When Hitler opens up the Eastern Front
in June,
it begins the largest military
confrontation in history.
With the Red Army outnumbering the
Germans by 3:1.
Hitler is convinced he can defeat it by
equipping his men with superior
firepower.
And he believes better means bigger.
>> Hitler wanted something that was
massive, almost phallically powerful.
The Krupp gun, for example.
>> The Krupp family have long been one of
Germany's finest makers of weapons.
Their railway guns have been used to
devastating effect in the defeat of
France.
The railway gun is not only powerful,
it's easy to transport.
One of their most effective guns is the
K5.
It sees action on the northwestern coast
of France [music] attacking British
shipping in the English Channel.
Weighing 240 tons, the K5 is capable of
firing a shell up to a distance of 40
miles.
But Hitler wants something even bigger.
So Krupps offer him the Schwerer Gustav
gun.
>> It weighed 1,350
tons. It had a barrel that was 30 m
long, the biggest gun ever. It could
fire a massive shell over 10 scores of
miles.
>> The Gustav is more than six times
heavier than the K5.
It's over 155 ft long and stands four
stories [music] tall.
It fires a shell weighing 10 and 1/2
thousand pounds.
And in the spring of 1942, it becomes
[music] the biggest artillery piece ever
used in combat.
Capable of obliterating an enemy fort
with just six shells.
In total, it fires 300 rounds [music]
during the siege of Sevastopol.
But for all its devastating power,
this super gun has major drawbacks.
>> It had to run on specially constructed
railway tracks. So, you might need a
couple of thousand men to lay the
railway.
You needed several hundred people just
to operate this gun.
>> Not only does it need a crew of 2,000 to
make it work, it requires 3 and 1/2 days
to assemble and can only fire 14 rounds
a day.
And it has an even bigger disadvantage.
>> A great big gun operating on specially
laid railway tracks is visible from the
air.
>> The Gustav is easy prey for the Allied
bombers.
Within a year, the Germans are forced to
stop using it.
Hitler's armies are still driving
forward, and he still insists on his
biggest best approach.
And crucially, it's Hitler himself who
dictates weapons development.
>> He believes he has got a fantastic
military knowledge, not just on the
battlefield, but also technologically as
well.
>> For many aspiring engineers and
scientists, there is one way to win
their Führer's favor.
>> He was amazed by anybody who'd come to
him with a new wonder weapon that might
devastate his enemies and win the war
for him.
>> Among those who come to him is a famous
car designer, the inventor of the
Beetle.
>> Ferdinand Porsche, the designer of the
Volkswagen car, he's kind of Hitler's
pal and he's saying, "Why don't you go
for some of these clever ideas that I'm
coming up with?"
>> Up to this point, it's the Panzer III
and the Panzer IV tanks that have been
the German workhorses.
And an unrivaled success in the famous
Blitzkrieg.
But when Hitler sees his enemies'
equivalents on the Eastern Front, he
knows he needs to upgrade.
>> They come up against the T-34 tank and
the KV-1 [music] tank.
Their own anti-tank guns are not
penetrating the thick armor on these
Russian tanks and [music] they've also
got bigger guns. They've got 76 mm guns
on the Russian tanks compared to the
lighter armament on the majority of the
German tanks.
>> Porsche's first great contribution comes
in August 1942
when he helps produce the notorious
Tiger tank.
Weighing 57 tons, it's massively
effective on both the Eastern and the
Western Fronts.
With the tank's devastating firepower
and its impregnable armor, the allies'
fear of it coins the phrase "Tiger
phobia".
>> The Tiger tank was a very serious
problem for the allies indeed. It was
bigger and more powerful than anything
the Western allies had.
>> But for all its success, the Tiger has
its problems.
It's unreliable and slow.
It guzzles fuel.
And it's so finely engineered, it's also
complicated to manufacture.
>> Um the trouble was that for the German
army, they just couldn't build enough of
them. Now, the chances of an Allied
crewman in a tank bumping into a Tiger
is actually relatively thin cuz there
just aren't enough to go around.
>> But for Hitler, it's not that it's
impractical, it's just not big enough.
So, Porsche comes up with something even
more impressive.
With armored plating up to 9 in thick
and at 190 tons, weighing the equivalent
of four 737 airplanes, the new machine
is ironically called the Mouse.
It's the largest tank ever built, but
Hitler wants it to be even larger.
>> The gun they hope to put on the tank is
128 mm. So, that was a massively
powerful gun.
When Hitler saw it on the Mouse, he just
thinks the gun looks too fiddly.
So, he encourages an even bigger gun to
be [music] placed on the tank. So,
they're actually starting to design a
150 mm gun, which is huge. It's just
ridiculous.
>> Hitler's so impressed with his tank, he
orders 150.
But the mighty Mouse just weighs too
much.
Few bridges can take the Mouse's
colossal weight. So, it's fitted with a
snorkel to go underwater.
It's too heavy to transport and with a
top speed of only 8 mph, the Mouse, like
the Gustav gun, is a sitting duck for
Allied aircraft.
By December 1943, when the first
prototype rolls off the production line,
it is wasted vital design time,
hardware, and manpower, which Germany
can ill afford.
Only two Maus tanks ever reach
completion.
>> In 1945, the Russians capture these two
remaining hulls. They fire some shells
at it. They have a look at it. The
honest truth is, it didn't take the
Russians too long to realize there is
nothing to learn here. This is a barking
mad idea, so it really doesn't actually
influence any design at all after the
war.
>> The Maus tank and the Gustav gun
demonstrate Hitler's belief in both the
power of size and his own military
genius.
So, next he turns his faith in big is
better to air transport for troops
and shows that not all his pieces of
military hardware are as completely
ineffective.
As the German army continues to advance
across the vast Eastern Front and the
huge flat open spaces of North Africa,
there's a growing demand for a big
transport aircraft.
Designer Willy Messerschmitt unveils the
Me 321 Gigant.
The Gigant is a glider designed to carry
troops and vital supplies across great
distances.
It has strange clam-shaped doors, and
with a 180-ft wingspan, it has the
potential to carry 20 tons in weight.
Yet, the Gigant is made almost entirely
out of wood and fabric.
It undergoes top secret testing [music]
and is being widely used by the end of
1941.
>> The Gigant, it was absolutely vast,
several stories high.
I can't remember how many soldiers it
held. Indeed, I'm not even sure whether
they know officially how many it held,
but certainly a couple of hundred.
>> The problem is it's so big, it needs
three planes to tow it off the ground.
It's heavy, difficult to steer, and
dangerous.
But rather than give up on the monster
glider, Hitler decides to build a
monster plane to tow it into the air.
Its name is the Zwilling.
Zwilling means twin in German.
The aircraft is constructed from two
Heinkel bombers plus an extra engine.
The Gigant successfully takes troops to
the front
using the Zwilling's towing power.
But Messerschmitt isn't satisfied.
Instead, he decides to make the Gigant
self-powered.
It's fitted with six engines.
The aircraft is so cumbersome and its
controls are so heavy, it needs a
physically strong seven-man crew to fly
it.
It is used on the supply routes to
Russia and ferries men and fuel to the
German army in North Africa.
But rumbling along at a speed of just
130 mph, it's vulnerable to Allied
fighters.
>> Large numbers of troops were killed when
these things crashed and landed in
inhospitable territory. We used a lot of
gliders,
but we had smaller gliders, which were
easy to control, and most of our
soldiers survived the impact perfectly
well.
When a Gigant came down in a forest or
smashed into the side of a hill, then
everybody was lost.
>> They're so unsafe, by the spring of
1944, production is halted, and none of
them survived the war.
By now, the tide of the war is turning.
>> In early 1944, it's it's becoming
evident to most Germans that they are
losing the war.
They are being driven back on the
Eastern Front, losing the war against
the Soviet Union.
>> Across Southern Britain, a million men
are secretly preparing for the Allied
assault of Normandy in Northern France.
And the Allied combined bombing
offensive is already grinding down the
Nazi war machine.
Hitler's air force is being overwhelmed,
and he needs a way to fight back,
particularly against the US Air Force's
daylight bombing raids.
>> From the German point of view,
how to stop these American formations of
bombers
coming and devastating their cities.
The real solution is to use fighters to
try and shoot them down.
And the best and most effective way of
doing this is a head-on attack at very
high speed.
>> [music]
>> Hitler turns once again to Willy
Messerschmitt, who this time offers him
jet power.
Jet technology has also been progressing
throughout the 1930s and 40s in Britain.
Thanks to pilot [music] and aeronautical
engineer Frank Whittle.
Whittle invents a jet engine, but in the
crucial early years of its development,
his ideas are not taken seriously.
[music]
>> He was viewed with a certain amount of
doubt [music] to say the least.
He did not get the support he should
have had.
What he needed, [music] of course, was
to be the idea to be seized on and money
to be poured into it.
>> But in Nazi Germany, where jet
technology is being developed
simultaneously,
the Nazi's ultra-progressive approach to
science and engineering means that full
backing is given to this new concept.
[music]
>> A lot of people don't realize how a jet
works, but it's actually incredibly
simple.
Just think, you have a a spindle with a
fan at the front and the back.
And it's spinning around,
and because it's got a fan at the front,
it's drawing air in.
>> These turbines
rotate,
compress the air, push the air further
back, and each time it gets pushed
further back,
the air gets compressed more and more
and more and more and more.
>> You then squirt some fuel into it, which
catches fire, roars out the back, and
spins the second fan,
but the second fan is joined to the fan
at the front.
So, now the front fan is going faster,
it's pulling in more air, which is
burning faster and turning the rear fan
even quicker.
That's what a jet is. It is incredibly
simple to understand.
>> By supporting the development of the jet
engine, Germany has gained a critical
advantage.
Perfectly demonstrated when
Messerschmitt unveils his Me 262
Schwalbe.
>> The Messerschmitt 262, in my opinion,
was the most formidable fighter of World
War II.
>> Introduced in summer 1944, it's the
best-equipped aircraft of its era.
It carries four 30-mm cannons and up to
12 55-mm rockets under each wing.
And its revolutionary design stuns the
allies.
>> When I saw it, I realized it was
something quite unusual.
Aerodynamically, it had a fuselage like
a shark.
And it had swept-back wings.
So, I knew we were dealing with
something quite different.
And its top speed was 568
mph. 125
mph faster than our fastest aircraft.
Now, this really shook us.
>> The first operational jet-powered
fighter enables the Germans to at last
challenge the Allied bombers.
>> The idea was that the 262 would get
above the bomber formation
and then it dive down on them.
The airplane was so fast that by the
time the gunners responded to seeing it,
it had gone. And they had passed it and
probably knocked out one [music] of the
bombers.
>> But then Hitler personally intervenes.
>> He was desperate to be able to do
bombing.
And he just asked Willy Messerschmitt,
"Can this
plane carry bombs?"
>> Instead of concentrating on defending
against the Allies, Hitler wants to
attack them.
So, he orders that it be converted to a
fighter-bomber.
>> If Messerschmitt said no, that would
have been the end of it. But when he cuz
he said yes, Hitler immediately jumped
on it as as the answer. An aircraft that
could drop bombs on Allied soldiers and
get away quick.
>> Hitler decrees that the fighter is
immediately modified to carry bombs for
action against the Allied invading
forces.
>> The problem was where were they going to
put the bomb? There was nowhere inside
the fuselage that they could do it. So,
the only place they could actually mount
it would be under here.
500 kilos was what it what it carried.
250 underneath here and another 250 kilo
bomb under there.
>> To enable it to carry the heavy bombs,
the Me 262 must be deprived of vital
ammunition and some of its cannons.
It weakens it as a fighter and nullifies
its amazing speed.
But calamitously, the changes mean these
jets aren't ready until August 1944.
By which time the Allies have already
invaded and are halfway across France.
Even so, in just 11 months service, the
Me 262 does claim more than 500 Allied
aircraft.
Thanks to Hitler's interference though,
its true potential as a jet fighter is
never realized.
With the Allies still controlling the
skies, Hitler needs something that can
help him turn things around and win the
war quickly.
A top-secret program.
Germany's cities are being devastated.
Hitler wants a weapon that can deliver
his enemy with a swift knockout blow.
He already has a top-secret program well
underway to do just that.
Hell-bent on offense, Hitler is
convinced German engineering can bring
him victory.
So, he turns to his best designers and
scientists.
What they come up with are the infamous
V-weapons.
>> Vengeance. You can't quite translate it,
but it means something like reprisal.
Getting our own back. Hitting back after
we've been wrongfully attacked.
>> The first of Hitler's reprisal weapons
is the V1 pulsejet flying bomb.
It uses a new lightweight version of jet
technology.
It has a range of 150 mi and a speed of
400 mph.
Able to produce 660 lb of thrust,
the V1 is yet another revolutionary feat
of German engineering.
>> Often called the first cruise missile to
be used in warfare,
a simple pilotless aircraft with a nose
cone full of explosives, cheap to
produce, mobile, easy to launch. The
launch site, the ski ramp launch sites
could be set up very quickly.
>> The V1 is guided via a rudimentary
compass mechanism
>> [music]
>> and is preset to travel a specific
distance.
Its first target is London.
In June 1944, just a week after the
Normandy landings, the first one is
launched.
Within a month, more than a hundred V1s
are hitting London every day,
terrorizing the city.
Launched from a number of sites across
northern Europe, in total, the V1 buzz
bombs kill more than 22,000 people.
Eric Brown is amongst the fighter pilots
ordered to stop the V1.
One of the techniques he has to use is
wing tipping.
>> The problem was if you got near to it
and shot it down,
if it exploded,
you were liable to be hit with the
debris from it.
So, we had to devise another method, and
that was to fly alongside it
and get your wing tip under its wing
tip,
and you then brought your wing tip up
and it rolled a V1 over.
You had to look down to see you weren't
going to do this over a town.
Wait till you got it into open country.
>> With the allies still struggling to
tackle the V1s, in September Hitler
unleashes his second reprisal weapon,
the V2.
The secret V2 rocket program has been
underway since 1936
and is the brainchild of visionary
scientist Wernher von Braun.
It's the world's first ballistic
missile.
It stands a monstrous 46 ft tall and has
a launch weight of nearly 13 tons.
It's also the world's first large-scale
liquid-propelled rocket.
>> In a rocket, you don't use atmospheric
oxygen like a jet does to burn your
fuel. You carry your oxidant aboard. It
might be hydrogen peroxide, it might be
liquid oxygen.
>> Inside the rocket's body, a combination
of ethyl alcohol and water and liquid
oxygen are delivered to a reaction
chamber by two rotary pumps.
The liquids then burn and expand to
create a high-pressure, high-speed
stream of hot gases, which upon leaving
the engine generates the thrust.
On launch, the V2 produces 55,000 lb of
thrust, which quickly increases to an
extraordinary 160,000 lb when maximum
velocity of 3,580
mph is reached.
It's guided by an advanced gyroscopic
system which sends signals to vanes and
to steering rudders on the rocket's
fins.
>> Within a minute or so, once it had got
up to speed,
the motor cut out and the rocket was
then under its own steam.
It would then glide under its own
momentum right up to the fringes of
space and then coast down.
Incredible thought that, isn't it?
>> The V2 actually becomes the first
man-made object to enter space.
Hitler's V2 offensive begins on the 8th
of September 1944
with a rocket aimed at Paris.
It quickly proves devastating.
Over several months, more than 3,000 V2s
are launched against Britain and across
Western Europe causing massive
destruction.
As the V2 flies at four times the speed
of sound, the 7,250
people it kills don't hear it coming.
The Allies have no way of stopping the
V2.
The only thing they can do is bomb its
production lines.
It's not until bombing raids are carried
out against V1 and V2 factories and
launch sites like this one at Lac au Pal
in northern France that Hitler's V2
program is quashed.
For his final attempt at retaliation,
Hitler rests his hopes on his first
love,
the big gun.
>> Valerie Noel is the supervisor of La
Forteresse de Mimoyecques, now a museum,
but formerly Hitler's top secret
underground launch site in northern
France, built exclusively for the
colossal V3.
>> This cannon was 127 m long, a
multi-charge one.
>> This was the Busy Lizzie, or the
Millipede, as it was called in German.
>> The V3 cannon is to be buried 100 m deep
underground for protection,
resting in a shaft and intended to
protrude out of an opening at the
surface,
pointing towards its target, London.
The London Gun, as it becomes known,
uses radically new technology.
>> And it had a series of barrel sections,
and at each section there were two
barrels alongside, in which an explosive
charge would fire. And the idea was that
as the shell moved up through the
barrel, these charges would fire one
after the other, propelling it faster
and faster and faster and faster.
>> Each time the shell would pass near
those additional charges, the speed of
the shell would be accelerated to obtain
a final speed of 1,500 m per second at
the mouth of the cannon.
>> The gun can fire its 150 mm shell up to
a distance of 95 mi,
more than twice as far as the Gustav
railway gun.
But Hitler's plans for the V3 are even
more ambitious.
He wants to build banks of these
cannons, grouped together in sets of
five.
>> So, look, here is the third firing
shaft, and you can see the light from
that one.
They had planned to build 10 firing
shafts, 50 cannons all together, 3,000
shells sent on to London per day.
>> The concept of guns designed to bombard
London relentlessly excites Hitler.
But again, the V3 proves a massive drain
on already scarce resources,
and testing doesn't go well.
>> They realized that the the cannon wasn't
as efficient as they thought it would
be.
So, they would have problems with the
shell, they would have problems with the
tubes, with the heat.
>> The main problem was timing the rate
>> [music]
>> at which these side barrels would
explode.
>> Then in July 1944,
before construction and testing is
complete,
the Mimoyecques launch site is knocked
out by a series of massive bombing
raids,
and then captured by the advancing
allies shortly afterwards.
As the Second World War enters its final
phase, Hitler is forced back onto the
defensive.
Critically, he still has to find a way
to protect his cities
now being razed to the ground by the
Allied bombers.
He needs something new and
revolutionary.
So, once [music] again, he turns to
German engineers to help him claw back
the initiative.
Nazi scientists are already secretly
designing, building, and testing a whole
host of strange, futuristic weapons.
They need something economical, fast,
and hard-hitting to knock the enemy out
of the sky.
Harnessing in miniature the same
technology behind the V2, Messerschmitt
offers up the 163B Komet.
>> It's an extraordinary aircraft.
Rocket-propelled.
Very, very fast.
>> To make the small, stubby-looking rocket
as light and as aerodynamic as possible,
the Komet [music] has no undercarriage,
instead taking off from a two-wheeled
trolley.
It's capable of climbing at a staggering
rate of [music] 10,000 ft a minute, and
can reach a speed of almost 600 mph.
Pilot Eric Brown becomes one of the few
people to have flown the Komet
when he tests a captured one at the end
of the war.
>> I was just
interested in seeing what rocket flight
would be like.
It was a revelation.
It was really like being in [music]
charge of a runaway train.
It was moving so fast
that your brain wasn't moving at the
right speed with it.
>> The Komet is designed to climb to a
maximum altitude of 39,000 ft
with the intent of taking out the Allied
aerial threat.
>> The idea was to pursue the bombers,
overtake them, and climb above them.
Probably about 2,000 ft above the bomber
stream.
Then cut the rocket engine,
start your stopwatch immediately. This
was vital
because you could not restart the engine
until 2 minutes had elapsed.
Dive down at a very high diving speed
onto the force and open up on them with
your 230 mm cannon.
>> After an attack, the Comet must return
to earth.
But now the pilot's job gets even more
difficult.
>> The Germans lost 42
aircraft exploding
on landing. Every one of them a fatal
accident.
Now,
because the fuels were so volatile,
>> the Comet is powered by a highly
dangerous cocktail of hydrazine hydrate
and methanol.
Without an undercarriage, it makes
landing it on a skid extremely
hazardous.
>> They had a jewel jettison system on it.
If you had any fuel left, you were
supposed to use the jettison system.
If you had even half a cupful
left [music] in the tanks
when you landed,
the impact of touchdown would explode
the fuel and literally
the whole thing just disintegrated.
I would come to the most dangerous
airplane I've ever flown.
>> It may be dangerous, but it works.
There are 16 confirmed instances of
bombers shot down by the Comet.
But despite its effectiveness, most of
the Comets are either grounded due to a
shortage of fuel or because the
airfields they need to take off from are
destroyed by bombing raids.
For Hitler, defeat looms.
German engineers are now desperately
racing to develop new technology.
But in the spring of 1945,
American, British, and Russian troops
close in on Berlin.
They capture German military bases and
munitions centers.
Some of the weapons they find stun them.
Like the Bachem Ba 349 Natter rocket
interceptor.
As with the Comet, it's another aircraft
created to knock out the Allied bombers.
And it's supposed to be a solution to
the problem of Germany's fast-depleting
airfields.
>> The Natter was designed for vertical
takeoff. They of course didn't need
runways.
>> Only requiring a small launch pad to
take off from, the Natter is supposed to
be far easier to hide and protect from
the enemy.
And made from plywood nailed and glued
together, it's also very cheap and easy
to manufacture.
For a country now being out mass
produced by the allies on a scale of
nearly four to one, it seems an
attractive proposition.
With its strange nose cone, the Natter
can carry a battery of 24 projectiles.
After launch, the rocket-powered Natter
is supposed to climb at speed to meet
the Allied bombers.
The pilot then fires the projectiles at
their target before both he and the
rocket engine jettison away from the
cockpit with parachutes.
As many as 36 Natters are built.
But unsurprisingly,
the program is abandoned after its first
and fatal manned test flight.
>> That's one airplane I would have refused
to fly I think because I think
it was doomed to disaster from the word
go.
>> The scattered remnants of the Natter
show just how desperate things have got
for Hitler.
But then US troops make a truly
startling discovery in a hangar in
central Germany.
It proves to be the most advanced
aircraft ever built.
>> In the final assembly hall, they found
the third prototype of the the 229
[music]
in its final stages of assembly. It was
only missing minor components, had not
yet test flown.
>> Partially dismantled by the German
engineers before their rapid escape,
this is the incredible Horton 229 flying
wing.
For the allies, it's one of Hitler's
most astonishing and mesmerizing
weapons.
The idea of the flying wing has obsessed
scientists since the 1930s.
>> One of the things that's very [music]
significant about the pure wing is that
it eliminates all forms of what
aeronautical engineers call parasitic
drag.
Bumps or protuberances, little bits
sticking out.
Speed is improved. Even maneuverability
in some ways is improved provided the
wing is designed properly.
>> Not only is the Horten 229
aerodynamically impressive, it's also
the first flying wing to use jet
technology.
It's designed in answer to German Air
Force Chief Hermann Göring's request for
a fighter-bomber.
It can deliver a 2,200-lb
payload, the same explosive capability
of the V1 and V2, at an incredible 620
mph.
But the war ends before the Horten gets
a chance to see operational service.
After the war, though, something even
more extraordinary is discovered about
this flying wing.
>> The original 229 was brought back to the
United States for study.
Still exists and it will eventually be
put on display. But in the meantime,
right here, we have a full-size replica.
>> Housed at the National Air and Space
Museum in San Diego, this model was
built to test the Horten 229's
visibility to radar.
>> It was found to be approximately 40%
less reflective
>> [music]
>> than a traditional fighter plane of the
day.
>> The plane's designers, brothers Reimar
and Walter Horten, have not only created
an aircraft that was aerodynamically
efficient, but also one partially
invisible to radar.
>> It had stealth as we know it now. We
didn't know about it then, but it had
stealth um capabilities
or characteristics.
And uh
this was just
the design and the material they were
using.
>> The Germans were very, very good at
radar, and the Hortons knew how
important radar detection was. So, they
actually made the first ever anti-radar
paint. They experimented with special
mixtures that they would coat [music]
the wings with in order to try and
minimize the radar signature.
>> This impregnated plywood radar-wave
absorbing skin, a special
carbon-composite glue used in place of
metal rivets, and its narrow profile are
all believed to make the aircraft harder
to detect. [music]
But, had the Hortons deliberately tried
to design an aircraft that was invisible
to radar?
As yet, no one can be certain.
>> I think there's a coincidence at work
here, and and the fact is that the
airplane by nature is more stealthy
because it's a wing and it provides a
smaller target. Design philosophy was to
make an airplane that was more
efficient, that was faster, that had
better range, and could reach ground to
height faster than other airplanes.
In those things, it would have succeeded
wonderfully.
>> Whether it was by accident or by design,
Hitler had produced the first-ever
stealth bomber.
The US Army is so impressed that they
shipped the Horton back to the United
States to learn its secrets.
With it go more than 1,500
German experts, engineers, and
technicians.
Amongst them, rocket scientist Wernher
von Braun.
Over the coming years, von Braun,
together with his team, use their
rocketry knowledge to form the basis of
America's ballistic missile program.
But, von Braun's influence will stretch
even further.
A variant of his V2, the Saturn V,
propels the first man to the moon.
The fact that German ingenuity and
engineering expertise become so
important to the West after 1945
demonstrates just what opposition the
Allies had found themselves up against
in the closing years of the Second World
War.
>> When you look at these things, you say,
"Well, just suppose they developed all
these amazing rocket piloting center.
>> [music]
>> Just suppose they'd had jet planes a
little bit quicker. Could they have won
the war?"
>> The critical point about all the German
super weapons is that they are too
little, too late.
These are weapons, if they could have
been mass produced earlier in the war,
or even produced on a much greater scale
in 1944,
might have made a major difference.
>> Luckily for the Allies, Nazi Germany's
amazing technological potential is
hindered by Hitler's insistence on
meddling in things he doesn't
understand.
Instead, it's his enemy that benefits
from German innovation and their
progressive approach to science.
>> [music]
>> Woo!